<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An examination of a late treatise of the gout wherein John Colbatch's demonstrations are briefly refuted, the College cleared from his scandalous imputations; and a short account of his vulnerary powder. By S. W. no inconsiderable branch of the College.</title>
            <author>S. W.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 101 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65251</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W107</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217645</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829300</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829300</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33737</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65251)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33737)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1940:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An examination of a late treatise of the gout wherein John Colbatch's demonstrations are briefly refuted, the College cleared from his scandalous imputations; and a short account of his vulnerary powder. By S. W. no inconsiderable branch of the College.</title>
                  <author>S. W.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 43, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed, for the author, and sold by the booksellers of London and Westminster,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Colbatch, John.  A treatise of the gout. (Cf. Wing C5013).</note>
                  <note>The "College" of the title is the Royal College of Physicians, London.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library, Oxford.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Colbatch, John, --  Sir, 1670-1729. --  Treatise of the gout --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Treatise of the gout.</term>
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Gout --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33737:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33737:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EXAMINATION OF A Late Treatiſe OF THE GOUT: Wherein <hi>John Colbatch</hi>'s Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations are briefly Refuted, the College cleared from his ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Imputations; And a ſhort Account of His Vulnerary Powder.</p>
            <p>By <hi>S. W.</hi> no inconſiderable Branch of the College.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Efficiam poſthác ne quenquam voce laceſſas.</hi> Virg.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, for the Author, and ſold by the Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:33737:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33737:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the</hi> Preſident <hi>and other</hi> Members <hi>of the Royal College of Phyſicians,</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>OUR Countrey is the moſt fam'd of any, in the World, for the <hi>Liberty</hi> we enjoy, and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity we have made to our Property by its excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Laws: Yet, I think Societies are, upon ſome occaſions, ſo very ſtrict, that to leſs diſcerning Eyes they may ſeem meer Monopolies. I muſt complain of my own hardſhips in this matter eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially; but to whom, I know not; for tis from <hi>You</hi> that all my misfortunes flow; and ſince this Error of the firſt <hi>Concoction</hi> cannot be ſo eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trieved among you, by Reaſon of the fault and defect in the Conſtitution that hinders People of ſingular parts, tho' now of a mean Office, at laſt to arrive to the liberty of being admitted a Fellow among you: to be a Licentiate will not go down, ſince <hi>Colbatch</hi> s admiſſion. I confeſs I did once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to have ſuppreſs'd all thoſe aſpiring thoughts, with conſiderations of Religion; but when I ſee ſcandalous Libels thrown about againſt you, and theſe ſo fitted to the Capacity of the Mob, that you think their Author below your wrath; I muſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my ſelf that my Religion obliges me to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure my Neighbour's good Name, and that the following defence of my old Maſters may entitle me a great deal better to a Diploma, than any thing this feigned friend of the College can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb facs="tcp:33737:3"/>
to; and may alſo prevent my Petitioning the King and Parliament to oblige you to do me Juſtice.</p>
            <p>But if we look into the merit of the Cauſe, it muſt be allowed me that I who have ſeen ſo many <hi>Diſſections,</hi> heard ſo many <hi>Lectures,</hi> over-heard ſo many <hi>Examinations</hi> of Young Phyſicians, I who have kept the <hi>Books</hi> written by our learned Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and have very often carried their <hi>Gowns</hi> and <hi>Caps,</hi> muſt be a great deal more knowing in all the difficult parts of Phyſick than <hi>He.</hi> Did I not hear the learned Dr <hi>Harvey</hi> talk after ſo lively a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Blood's Circulation, and his Generation <hi>ex Ovo,</hi> that I vow and ſwear, I have thought I have ſeen the Drunken Heart ſpew out its Blood into the great Artery, and I could trace its Stages thro' the whole Body? then for the buſineſs of the <hi>Valves,</hi> I have ſo lively an Idea of them, that I can ſhow you them only by look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon you Skin. But as for the Generation, that did ſo tickle me when I was a Young Man, that I eaſily apprehended the falſe Notions of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Phyſicians upon that Subject: I can yet give a very plain deſcription of that genital liquor at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacking the ripe Egg in the <hi>Ovarium,</hi> and a great deal more that I ſaw at ſome diffections he made to King <hi>Charles</hi> II. nay, for my part, I thought all this matter was ſo clear that I wonder the Dr never found the way to get a Male-child at one bout of a Conſummation Action. We have Sir <hi>George Ent</hi>'s Book too that defends his Circulation <hi>contra omnes mortales,</hi> for as eaſy a matter as <hi>Colbatch</hi> thinks it; but had he had to do with <hi>Pariſanus,</hi> the old fellow wou'd have plaid the Devil with him, and his Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gature too; then came Dr <hi>Gliſſon</hi> with his <hi>Livers, Stomachs,</hi> and <hi>Guts</hi> ſo nicely prepar'd, that the <hi>Secretion</hi> of the <hi>Gall,</hi> the Digeſtion, the buſineſs of the <hi>Chyle,</hi> and the <hi>Excrements</hi> were ſo familiar to me, that I had no difficulties left me in that affair. But as for Dr <hi>Willis,</hi> he was the firſt that
<pb facs="tcp:33737:3"/>
taught us to diſſect the Brain, that we might ſee all its parts; when Phyſicians before him were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to ſlice it down like a piece of <hi>Pudding,</hi> and when <hi>Des Cartes</hi> did ſee his <hi>Glandula Pinealis</hi> ſtick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a ſlice like a Plum, he was a great Maſter who could hit upon it once in five times; but our Dr cou'd ſhow you any thing, and when you pleas'd; he trac'd out all the Nerves, and deſcrib'd nobly the whole Brain: I have heard him talk of his <hi>Anima Brutorum,</hi> his Books of <hi>Fermentation, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rins, Fevers, &amp;c.</hi> with that exactneſs, that I muſt own that I have had ſometimes the Vanity to think my ſelf as learned a Phyſician as himſelf. Dr <hi>Wharton</hi> began firſt to number the Glands, and to undeceive the World of a fancy they had about <hi>Parenchymatous</hi> ſubſtances. Next came Dr <hi>Lower,</hi> who told us of the Hearts being <hi>Muſcular,</hi> and put it under the ſame laws; he tells us in the ſame Book of putting Blood out of one Animal into another, and what advantage that may be in cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſome Diſeaſes. Dr <hi>Havers</hi> gives us a Book of the Make of the Bones, and Dr <hi>Riddley</hi> gives us a Lecture upon the Brain, tho' a <hi>Frenchman</hi> one <hi>de Vuyſſens</hi> had made Dr <hi>Willis</hi>'s way more clear, yet not ſo much neither, but that the Dr has done it in greater order. Dr <hi>Garth</hi> read very finely upon <hi>Reſpiration</hi> and the uſe of the <hi>Lungs:</hi> Dr <hi>Liſter</hi> has oblig'd us with the Anatomy of <hi>Snails,</hi> and Dr <hi>Cockburn</hi> with an <hi>O Econom. Animalis.</hi> Of Bota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naiſts we have had a vaſt number, and lately Dr <hi>Sloan</hi> has given us an excellent account of the <hi>Plants</hi> of the Leeward Iſlands: Pharmacians, a great many, and lately Dr <hi>Bates.</hi> But for the Theory and practice of Medicin, no Countrey has exceeded us: in my time <hi>Willis</hi> both for the Theory and the Practice, Dr <hi>Charleton,</hi> Sir <hi>Theoder Mayern,</hi> Dr <hi>Bates,</hi> Dr <hi>Morton,</hi> and Dr <hi>Cockburn,</hi> who firſt told us how they are ſick at Sea.</p>
            <p>Now, can any Man think that I can be ſuch a blockhead, as to have liv'd among all theſe Maſters
<pb facs="tcp:33737:4"/>
in Medicin, to be bred up as it were at the foot of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> and for ſo long a time; and not to be better qualified for my <hi>Admiſſion</hi> than a fellow that either cannot <hi>think,</hi> or at leaſt cannot tell us what he thinks, and yet is ſo vain as to eſteem himſelf more knowing, than any of your worthy and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Members; one of whom he attacks, becauſe he<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s Dead, one ſtill alive, and by Name; and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he has only the courage to hint at, tho' he has told his ſtory ſo plainly over the Town, that 'tis now no great difficulty to know him: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I may hope that my thus proving a dutiful Servant, in giving my ſelf all this trouble, may give me greater pretences to a Diploma, and to be more and more,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt Obedient, Humble Servant, S. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:33737:4"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE TO John Colbatch.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R Book fell firſt into my hands on</hi> Aſh-Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſday, <hi>after I came from Church, and I was glad to think you had hit upon an abſolute Cure of the</hi> Gout, <hi>a demonſtrative one at leaſt, as you pleaſe to call it, in the frontiſpiece. Your Dedication ſmelt ſomewhat of Gratitude, which is ſtill well; but when I found this demonſtration was to be turn'd upon Acid and Alkali, or a thing we do not underſtand, I began to ſuſpect your knowledge; yet, I thought it poſſible that new lights might be diſcovered even by you, in this matter, and ſurely you had not the Impudence to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe us a Demonſtration of a thing we know nothing of, after a great deal of enquiry; and really when I lookt firſt into your Preface you wou'd make us expect no leſs than Revelation: but all this ſoon vaniſh'd into Dream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Aſſerting, Defaming downright all foreign Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, then the leſſer half of the College it ſelf, and next the greater, for really the praiſe you give them is ſo invidiouſly turn'd, that tis one of the worſt pieces of Satyr. The Scene thus odly chang'd, very ſtrangely at leaſt as to my expectation, rais<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d in me quite other ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions: my Church thoughts were not the very ſame; my paſſion grew almoſt into fury, to ſee my</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:33737:5"/>
Maſters ſo ill us'd, and one whom Nature had laid aſleep, and forbid us to remember him to his diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; yet his Aſhes were to be rais d for your trifle about the <hi>Gout.</hi> I confeſs I cou'd hold no longer, but the duty that s incumbent upon every man to defend his own, or his friend s Reputation, made me find ſome time from buſineſs to become an Author, tho' that was when I had attempted a ſecond reading, and after ten days. 'Tis the defence of all foreign Phyſicians, and a great many of our own that I have undertaken; a task I acknowledge too bold for me, with any one but your ſelf; and ev n theſe few that are excepted, muſt fall too when you are out of the apprehenſions of an Anſwer, or any other inconveniency from them: this is no forc d and unnatural concluſion; for, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your turning over Books to no purpoſe, as you ſay very well, foreign Phyſicians and my Maſters are agreed in moſt things of Phyſick; ſo that if your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign were to deſtroy <hi>Opinions,</hi> and lay under no fears of <hi>Men,</hi> you might have as eaſily run down all the College, as Ignoramus's, as you have done the learned men abroad: all theſe foreigners ſince the beginning of the World, all our dead Gentlemen, and a third of what's alive; ſurely my living Maſters that are ſpar'd cannot have better pretences than They; nay, I le an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for them, that they re aſham'd on your behalf, and angry too, that you have parted them from ſo good company; but eſprcially that you huve join'd them to your ſelf: Have not you done Dr. <hi>Cole</hi> a great deal of honour, in obtruding upon him your ridiculous jargon, and to call them his Opinions, Opinions he was very fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar with, or becauſe you are the firſt that vends em, opinions that he has lenrn't from you? Is there any ſuch ſtuff, in his Book <hi>de Secretione Animali,</hi> his letter of an Apoplexy, or his Book of Agues? if my memory fails me not, he s among one of your Dunces that make that Diſeaſe proceed from the Acidity of the Blood, as Dr. <hi>Jones</hi> does, and yet you may make him ſay here, that 'tis an Alkali that's the Original of that ſickneſs; old People, men ſay, are twice Children, yet he is not quite
<pb facs="tcp:33737:5"/>
ſo old, as to forget what he ſaid lately, to chatter after you: but ſince you uſe your Friend, your Patron no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I think your Doctors you make War upon have no reaſon to complain.</p>
            <p>In this Preface of yours, you have got into a Cant of <hi>Experimental knowledge, Experiments</hi> upon the <hi>Blood,</hi> and ſuch things you underſtand, and uſe the very ſame way that <hi>Enthuſiaſts</hi> do the Scripture: theſe are the beſt help to Natural Knowledge, as the Scripture are to Divine; but all this meer Jargon, Cant and Nonſenſe in your mouth who cannot under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them: and in my opinion the only way of proſelyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you, muſt be the ſame that the Church-men take with their Enthuſiaſts, to deſpiſe you. Are not you a rare Fellow to pretend to make an Experiment, who after all your toyl, all your reading, and all your Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition, are pleas'd to tell us that <hi>Phyſicians have hitherto unanimouſly agreed that Acids have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded in all Diſeaſes,</hi> this is as wonderful an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage as you have gain'd by reading of them; for 'tis manifeſtly falſe, and if we were to look into the ſtate of Phyſick in former Ages, or ev'n in our own time, we can find no ſuch <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Conſent; but now when I think of it, you only ſaid if turning over of Books wou'd do it, that you ſhou'd reſt ſatisfied; but that will not do; nay diſtilling, and combining of Liquors ſo long as your eyes are open, will never make one Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, without ſome Book-learning, which to you is a bug-bear. You ſee how well an accompliſh'd Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man you are like to prove for making Experiments, and ſo you have very good reaſon to ſay that in your Introduction you have made uſe of a Familiar and eaſy Experiment to confirm the truth of your New Hypothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis; and if any one ſhall take upon them to anſwer what you have ſaid in this, or any of your former Pieces, you expect that they ſhould back their Arguments with Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments, or you ſhall take no notice of them. What good ſervice your Familiar Experiment is like to do you, turn the leaf, and there you ll find it: but pray, if one may ask queſtions, tell me what Syrup of Violets it ſelf
<pb facs="tcp:33737:6"/>
is, Acid or Alkalin; according to this Familiar Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment, 'tis nothing; for Syrup of Violets, added to Syrup of Violets diſſolv d in an aqueous Body, may aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the quantity, but will ſtill be blue; <hi>Ergo</hi> tis nothing, becauſe neither Acid nor Alkali: the next time you write, be ſure to make a Syrup of Violets prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, <hi>h. e.</hi> every thing that does not change the Colour, is Violaceous; and find ſome Diſeaſe to be made or Cur<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d by it, ſo there will be Three, and <hi>Muſae gaudent Numero Impari,</hi> the principles of <hi>Sal, Sulphur,</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> are Three, <hi>Des Cartes</hi>'s are Three, and yours are Three; but this I'm affraid you won't like, becauſe you affect ſingularity.</p>
            <p>And as for anſwering your pieces, I know no body will be at the pains, but a Porter; nay, I'le promiſe you that when I had done, I had a great diſpute with my ſelf if I ſhou'd do you the honour: but a little for my Maſters, and helping off the Bookſeller with the damn d Copy, did prevail; but here I faithfully promiſe and ſwear, that no more of my Stoln time from other buſineſs ſhall be employ'd that way. But, pray, Why are all your Books <hi>Pieces?</hi> nothing but Artillery ſounds with you ſince you was in <hi>Flanders:</hi> the Preface before, was Powder and Ball, and now Pieces for the Powder and Ball; not ſo, good Member, your Pieces are harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs things enough, any body may attack them, and that more eaſily, and with more ſafety than nail d up Cannon, and you ſee the following Sheets are an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of an Ordinary fellow.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33737:6"/>
            <head>AN EXAMINATION OF A New Treatiſe OF THE GOUT.</head>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>SEmper ego auditor tantum, nunquamne reponam,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vexatus toties rauci Theſeide Codri?</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Or for our better underſtanding, as Mr <hi>Dryden</hi> and I, with a little liberty, will ſing it:</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Still ſhall I hear, and never quit the ſcore<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Stunn'd with</hi> Colbatche'<hi>s nonſence o're and o're.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>I have been quiet theſe forty years, becauſe I was always hearing ſomething that inform'd me; but now to have Libels upon our learned Members, by one who has not learn d his Inſtitutions, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable; and however he may be below their notice, as he really is, yet he cannot eſcape me, who have been charm'd ſo long with their Learn
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33737:7"/>
ing. But to do this as ſhortly as his want of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, uſeleſs repetitions, and ridiculous malice will allow me, I will only conſider the ſtrength of his pretences, and diſcover their weakneſs from ſuch ſolid maxims, as I have either heard or read that my Maſters do ſuppoſe; and reſerving his Preface for mine, the firſt thing we ſhall conſider ſhall be his Introduction; which I ſhou d take to be the moſt modeſt thing of the whole Book, were it not that he pretends his principles are ſo very obvious, that they are to be ſeen thorow by any body, and yet they have been remov'd from the eye of Phyſicians. The familiar experiment is, <hi>That all</hi> Acids, <hi>ſuch as Oyl of Vitriol, Oyl of Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur</hi> per cam panam, <hi>Spirit of Nitre, Spirit of Salt, Vinegar,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>being poured into Syrup of Violets in any aqueous Vehicle, will immediately turn it from a Blue to a very Red Colour; and as the Acid is more or leſs ſtrong, ſo will the Red Colour be of a deeper or paler Dye. On the other hand, all manifeſt Alkalies, ſuch as lixivious Salts, all the volatile Spirits and Salts, ſuch as Spirit and Salt of Hartſhorn, Spirit and Salt of Sal Armoniac, Salt of Vipers,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>will turn the Syrup of Violets, or a ſolution of it, either in Spring Water, or in any other aqueous Vehicle, from a Blue into a Green Colour; and as the Alkali is more or leſs ſtrong, ſo the Green Colour will be of a paler or a deeper Dye.</hi> From this he concludes, that if the Serum of the Blood change this ſolution of Syrup of Violets into a Red, it muſt be Acid; and if it changes it into a Green colour, poſitively Alkalin; and confirms this farther with a piece of Logick, which ſhews ſufficiently that he has no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Univerſity breeding, without his tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling us ſo; and notwithſtanding the expence of Money he has been at, in acquiring this Learning, all he ſhews is the <hi>Ergo,</hi> ſtrangely brought in. But pray, Mr Member of the Royal Colledge of Phyſicians, do you think that becauſe you were an Apothecary, and made up the Doctor's Hyſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33737:7"/>
Juleps and Gargariſms, and ſaw ſometimes Spirit of Hartſhorn added to the Waters which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd ſome of the Syrup of Violets; or at other times, Spirit of Vitriol, Niter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> added to ſome ſuch Tinctures, and to make this Red or Green Colour: Do you think, I ſay, that theſe Phyſicians had never ſeen theſe changes as well as you? That muſt not be ſuppos d even among foreign Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans (for thoſe, and ſuch as are dead, or want a name, you only are pleas'd to expoſe) but how came it that they never fell upon this demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of yours, ſurely 'tis not ſo much out of reach; but the reaſon you may have, when I'll ſhow you immediately that you have diſcover'd nothing at all. Firſt, ſome Phyſicians, and thoſe moſt Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners, have ſaid that the principles of mixt Bodies were an Acid and an Alkali, tho they have had vaſt difficulties even to deſcribe them ſo, that we cou'd know what they wou'd be at; and truly yours is no better; for of all the mixt Bodies, how many are there that will give your Water and Syrup of Violets a Red or a Green Colour? not the thouſandth part, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently not the thouſandth part of mixt Bodies are Acid or Alkalin, or the thouſandth part of mixt Bodies have no compounding Principles, <hi>h. e.</hi> they are ſomething and nothing: Yet 'tis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry natural to think, with one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f my nam'd Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, that if Acids and Alkalies are the true In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients or Components of Bodies, and that they concur as principles in their action, and bear Contre-parts in this action; then becauſe the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of either upon the other, may be augment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, diminiſhed or loſt, and this is to be faulty or vitious; therefore, or <hi>ergo,</hi> tis evident, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of em may have its defects, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that the blame ſhould not be laid upon one: <hi>h. e.</hi> ſuppoſing the principle of Alkali and Acid, Dr. <hi>Blankard</hi> and the Member, are both wrong; tho I confeſs if Acid and Alkali were any thing,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33737:8"/>
Dr. <hi>Blancard</hi> is moſt in the right; for the ſerum of the Blood, in the healthieſt People makes ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther no ſuch alterations of Red or Green; and when it does in that circumſtance, 'tis always to the Green, and conſequently the Blood in heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſt People is Alkalin; and becauſe that Conſtitution of the Blood that gives us Health can never be the ſame when we are Sick, and ſince the Blood when we are in Health is Alkalin, it muſt not be ſuppoſed ſo, when we are ſickly, but rather ſomething of a different and oppoſite temper: and becauſe that is to be Acid, <hi>ergo,</hi> our ſickneſſes do all proceed from an Acid, according to Dr. <hi>Blankard,</hi> againſt the Royal Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; now hehimſelf has given judgment upon ſuch ridiculous inferences as he makes, that they ought to be kickt out of a Commonwealth, for endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to impoſe upon Mankind: <q>And truly this is the only thing in the whole Book he and I ſeem moſt agreed upon; only I think we ſhou'd begin with him.</q> But ſuppoſing that that were an Acid which changes a ſolution of Syrup of Violets with Water into a red Colour, and that an Alkali, that changes it into Green; and that all mixt bodies made thoſe changes, and none elſe, <hi>h. e.</hi> let us have this Hypotheſis in its beſt light; yet it is ſo precarious and obſcure, that it cannot help us in the underſtanding one Phoeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menon; we know not their properties and powers, nay, one of them he ſuppoſes more uſeleſs than a Cypher; pray what knowledge can we attain to by knowing that a Triangle is a Figure that has three angles, or a Chiliogonum has a thouſand, without knowing any of its properties and rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to other Figures in practice for the uſe of Man? We don't apprehend by this that the three Angles of any Triangle are equal to two right Angles, and that the whole thouſand Angles in an Chiliogonum are but equal to four right Angles, and much leſs do we gain all the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33737:8"/>
and knowledge that the Doctrine of plain and Spherical Trigonometry affords us, by can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſſing Triangles upon different occaſions. Now I ſay, That if we could arrive to as uſeful a piece of knowledge, by ſuppoſing his Acid and Alkali to be what he deſcribes 'em, by demonſtrating their properties as evidently as we ſee thoſe of the mentioned Example, he might, for me, call the one <hi>Bow-Church,</hi> and the other the <hi>Royal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change:</hi> but on the contrary, all that ever we are to know of them is, that the one can make Syrup of Violets, diſſolved in any aqueous body, Red, and the other can make it Green. The poor Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers and Mathematicians that knew nothing of Syrup of Violets and Water, were at a ſad loſs. But pray, Mr. Member of the Royal College, ſince all the Phoenomena in Nature are to be accounted for by thoſe two principles, except the inconſiderable ones about Motion and Reſt, Light and Darkneſs, Magnetiſm, and a great many other, (of this kind) <q>too many here to inſert,</q> I'm affraid that all the Phaenomena are to follow; yet perhaps you are confident of all thoſe of your own Trade, and that they may ſtand your friends, except it may be that little ſort of motion of the Blood, which the Fools of Phyſicians call the Baſis in the O Economy, and curing Diſeaſes; but let us except that, and tell us the buſineſs of ſeeing from Acid and Alkali, why we have a Pulſe? And I'm ſure, that if you cannot do that, you cannot tell us whether a Stone ſees or not, at leaſt you cannot be uſeful to any that ſuffer in their ſeeing. Pray, good Mr. Member, now tell me, why I, when I was a young Man could not ſee any thing ten Yards be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me, without the help of a Glaſs, and now when I am old, I can ſee ten times further, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſuch help, and other Men of my acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance that accuſed me of blindneſs cannot ſee their own length now without a Glaſs? One thing more I would beg of you, and that is, that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33737:9"/>
when I am a Doctor, and muſt feel my Patients Pulſe, how we ought to have a Pulſe at all, and what kinds of Pulſes tell me that my Patient is Sick, and all this from the Combination and Privy Councel of Acid and Alkali, where you are Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, and can tell all their tricks? Moreover, ſettling our knowledge upon change of colour is the moſt uncertain thing in the World; not only becauſe I have ſeen Dr. <hi>Slaer</hi> take two Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanous liquors, that were as white as Water, yet, by putting them together ſoon chang'd into 20 Colours, ſome ſmoakt, ſome grew thick from being the thineſt ſubſtances I ever ſaw, and a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſuch tricks which are uſeful to be tried, but I never knew of the principle that could ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for them, tho' ſuch experiments afford us many concluſions about the uncertainty of human Underſtanding; nay, I have ſeen Mr. <hi>Boyle,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Newton</hi> at a deadly work about this buſineſs of Colour, and I am told that <hi>Des Cartes</hi> and Mr. <hi>Newton</hi> have exchanged many a Letter upon that Subject; tho' we believe that Mr. <hi>Newton</hi> had the beſt by much. Now, Mr. Member, don't you think that I have given you a very good reaſon, for former Phyſicians making no account of your Shop Experiments, they have ſeen a Thouſand times, but have left you to take up with it, for no body elſe wou d. Indeed you are in the right to make your appeal to the Mob about your diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery; for they know nothing of the matter: but Gentlemen are generally of ſo liberal an Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, that tho' they cou'd not diſpute the fact, yet they have the good Manners to think every thing true any one tells them, to his knowledge, to be matter fact; yet I le aſſure you that your Concluſions and theirs will be vaſtly different.</p>
            <p>This being premis d, we ſee what a certain foundation he has laid for himſelf; yet he thinks it ſo certain that in the 5th page he tells us, <q>That an ounce or two of Blood is to be ſpared in any
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33737:9"/>
caſe. Again, It will plainly appear by this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment, That the Blood of ſuch perſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds with Alkalies; and if ſo, why ſhould we croud in more Alkalies, unleſs it were to prolong the Diſtemper, to increaſe the number of Fees.</q> Here he ſhows abundance of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Honeſty; for in the firſt he ſuppoſes that an Ounce or two of Blood may be ſpared in any caſe, which is ſo very contrary to what I have heard my Maſters talk about, Revulſion and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivation, that nothing can be more; for if the Blood is brought more to one part than another, by the different ways of bleeding, as this Doctrine plainly intimates; then it may happen that we ſhall bring Blood to ſome part, upon occaſions, in a very ill and unlucky time, unleſs we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the buſineſs of Revulſion and Derivation ſomewhat exactly; but this is neither an Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion peculiar to him, nor is it my deſign to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer his Book to every particular, but only where he ſets up for himſelf, or aſſerts common opinions too peremptorily; and therefore I will only ſay to his Honeſty, That that is very ſingular, if he keeps his Patients long under his hand for gains ſake; yet by what he ſays, one wou'd think him a great Fool or Ignorant; for to heighten a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe as he talks, is to kill the Patient out-right, and ſo farewel Fees, which is his <hi>primum mobile,</hi> and a principle he's more fond of than Acid or Alkali; for I m inform'd he valu'd his Book a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Bookſellers at twenty Guineas, which he ſaid he wanted to buy a pair of Geldings to put into his new Coach. But after he has made ſo great advances by his demonſtrations, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins ſtill to challenge the ignorance and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty of Phyſicians, whom he makes a ſet of Fools or Knaves, and ſometimes both. <q>People, ſays he, muſt long ſince have known the truth of this hypotheſis, or they muſt not: If they have not known it, then it is plain they have grop<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33737:10"/>
in the dark, and they have cur'd Diſeaſes with as much certainty as a blind Man can catch a Hare, as the Proverb is, when they ſpeak of any thing that is very unlikely. If they have known it before, then the giving of Alkalies at the rate that has been done, is a plain argument againſt them that they have not acted like ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men. But I dare acquit them from this charge, I do believe they have ſworn <hi>in Verbo Magiſtri.</hi> And becauſe a few Book-learn'd Gentlemen have dreamt that the Bloods abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Acids has been the cauſe of Diſeaſes, therefore right or wrong it muſt be ſo, tho it be contrary to the moſt obvious and plain experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</q> So firm an Hypotheſis being once eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, his conſequences muſt be ſo plain and evident that nothing can withſtand them; and therefore he catches the poor Phyſicians in this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitable Dilemma, <q>People, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> Truly, good Mr. Member, I told you juſt now, that your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment has been ſeen often every day, but the Hypotheſis you raiſe upon it, is unworthy of any ones ſight but your own; but ſince you have got within your Dilemma, as Conjurers are ſaid to be within a Circle for their defence from the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, that we may give you ſtory for ſtory, I will, for once, ſuppoſe that they knew nothing of the matter, and yet I cannot ſee how they cur'd by gueſs, or groped in the dark, ſince they had more certain Rules which you ſeem to deſpiſe, and I'm ſure you know nothing of; and what <hi>lumieres</hi> you have got from this Hypotheſis, we ſhall find by your following obſervations; tho having ruined your foundation already, the thing is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of it ſelf. Again, we ſuppoſe that they did know it, tho no otherways than that the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis of Acid and Alkali is the moſt precarious ſuppoſition in the world, and that they knew Dr <hi>Blankard</hi> fond, tho modeſtly, of this Caſtle in the Air, and you a peremptory, dictating Block-head,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33737:10"/>
maintaining this ill-grounded ſtuff, and defaming Men of Learning to defend it; and in that ſenſe they were not confined to your giving of Acids upon all occaſions, and to deſpiſe the greater part of Simples, which they muſt needs do; ſince the greater part are either Alkalies, in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon acceptation, or nothing at all. I ſaid in the <hi>common Acceptation,</hi> becauſe I am one of thoſe who deſires no kind of jargon in phyſical know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. But what a fine excuſe you make for them, I think the common-wealth of learningought to grace your Birth-day with a Panegyrick upon it; that men of learning who will own no other Motto but <hi>Nullius in verba,</hi> yet you'll bedaub them with your impudence <hi>jurare in verbo</hi> (as you call it) <hi>Magiſtri;</hi> I muſt tell you that in governs both the <hi>Accuſative</hi> and <hi>Ablative Caſes,</hi> and ſo it may be good Grammar, which I'm ſure is more than you know; but in the ſenſe you deſign it, 'twas never us d but in the <hi>Accuſative:</hi> But pray you what Maſters' words do you find your College Oath bind you to, or what Maſter is that other Phyſicians follow; ſince they did ſhake off <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> the antient Guides of former Phyſicians, we ſee none other ſet up, but every one wou'd make Proſelytes, or inſtruct with the force of reaſon; they declare, that we may learn a great deal from, and ought to read <hi>Hipp. Gal. Avicen, &amp;c.</hi> on one ſide and all the moderns, of whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſect, on the other, but not to fight for the Infallibility either of <hi>Hippocr.</hi> or <hi>Van Helmont;</hi> but theſe old Gentlemen are none of your acquaintance, and therefore for once, I crave your Mercy, for introducing them into your Company. But pray Mr Member, muſt a man be ſaid to <hi>jurare in verba,</hi> that will not blindly follow all the nonſenſe that an impudent fellow wou'd obtrude upon him; if ſo, then I'le pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe you <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> will be the word ſtill.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:33737:11"/>
Now to what you ſay of a few Book-learn'd Gentlemen's dreams about Acids, being the ſource of all other Diſeaſes; I don t ſay that you'll own my Maſters Book-learned, but we ſee few of them either fond of Acid or Alkalies being the cauſes of Diſeaſes; but if one of them muſt needs be ſo againſt all ſenſe and reaſon, I told you before that Dr <hi>Blankard</hi> appealing to your experiment, has prov'd it ſo, without Book; ſurely you could not have thought that. I don t think the reſt of this Paragraph worthy my conſideration, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally becauſe I was by when Mr <hi>Boyl</hi> s Dialogiſts were at a hot diſpute about the power of Fire, in bringing out the firſt principles of Mixt Bodies, where it was carried in the <hi>Negative,</hi> after many a learned Speech; but you were not worthy of ſuch a Converſation, nor I neither; but I was Door-keeper, and did ſometimes peep in, and took care to over-hear as much as poſſibly I could; and tho I'm no Book-learn'd Man, nor a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, yet I was told that That was all in print; I think they call'd it the <hi>Sceptical Chymiſt.</hi> Now here was a learned man, that was for trying a thouſand tricks upon <hi>Blood,</hi> and every thing, without ever dreaming of eſſential and elementa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry princlples, as ſome of the common Chymiſts about this town, who were only employ'd about his Furnace, have done ſince; and for any thing I know, you may have got ſome Learning by blowing his <hi>Bellows,</hi> as I have by carrying of <hi>Gowns</hi> and <hi>Caps.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reſt of this Book to the 10th page, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining nothing but Conqueſt and the Ignorance of others, I muſt paſs it over, becauſe I cannot be able to conſider it, without letting ſlip ſome things as undiſcreet as his are. Only I think that a Man of his Policy and Underſtanding, wou'd at leaſt have repreſented his Antagoniſts as more knowing, and of more Experience, that ſo he might lay his way for a Glorious Conqueſt, and now if
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33737:11"/>
he is ſtruck with the Servant of theſe Ignorants, what a damnable misfortune is it to fall by the Jaw-bone of an Aſs. But the 1ſt §. of the 10th page, is ſo full of Inſtruction and Knowledge, that it requires our ſerious conſideration; and therefore we'll ſet it down at length. <hi>For want,</hi> ſays he, <hi>of our taking pains in making Experiments, has been the only cauſe of our ſo long building the Foundation of our Practice upon ſo falſe a Bottom; and I hope, that what I have ſaid will excite the Phyſicians of our Age to make ſuch Experiments, that thereby we may act upon ſome ſort of certainty.</hi> The Phyſicians of our own Age, but more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly of our own Nation, and amongſt them in a more eſpecial manner thoſe of our College, have made more and greater diſcoveries in Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my than ever were made before, I mean in the Anatomy of the ſolid Parts. <q>But as for the Fluids, thoſe parts wherein the Cauſe and ſeat of moſt Diſeaſes lurk, they have in a great meaſure been neglected: But the College a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds with Men of ſuch large Capacities, that if once they ſet about that noble work, I doubt not they will ſoon perfect it, to the great ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and Advantage of all Mankind.</q> This Paragraph conſiſts of three conſiderable Members, the firſt is the Cauſe why Medicin has not made greater advances, the praiſe of the Anatomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal diſcoveries in our Age, but more eſpecially in our own Nation, and the third an Encomium up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the College, a little healing after his Cauſticks and Inciſions, as good Chyrurgeons generally do work to the ground of ſordid and ſinuous Ulcers, ſuch as he has or will make the preſent Members, if he can but out-live them. But pray Mr. Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Royal College, do you pretend to be the firſt beginner of making Experiments; truly they'l be well made, when I dare challenge you to tell me whether a Stone ſees, hears, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or not; but have we not diſcover'd to us by the affiduous
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33737:12"/>
labours of learned Men, a more perfect know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the make of our own Body, the convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances of its liquors, and the Circulation of the Blood; have we not noble Experiments about our Body, and its liquors being affected by ambient bodies, compariſons made, and Hiſtories of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſons that have been by the combination of Salts with Salts, Liquors with Liquors, and even trials of all thoſe upon our Liquors. I'm of the opinion that we ought to proceed with all theſe trials; but how to abſolve, and what uſe is to be made<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of thoſe Obſervations I am convinced that you do not know; we ſhall ſee immediately what familiar Theories you raiſe in the curing of the <hi>Gout,</hi> from all thoſe diſcoveries; what vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons you make, and what reaſon you give for your Medicins; I'm affraid we ſhall find you ſo uncapable to apprehend the circumſtances of a nice Experiment, that you are not even able to give us a genuin Hiſtory of a Diſeaſe. I agree with you that I believe that the Phyſicians ſince the Reſtoration of K. <hi>Ch.</hi> II. have made greater diſcoveries in the Anatomy than any; but for my part I don't pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to know the Doctors abroad; I have told you of my Maſters that have been fam'd for ſome new piece of Learning, and all that in my time, ſo I'm apt to believe what you ſay; tho' I have ſometimes heard of a <hi>French</hi> Fellow that told us a Story of the Lacteal Veſſels, when the noiſe of diſcoveries was ſo great at home; I have heard of <hi>Bartholin, D'Graaf,</hi> and ſome others I cannot call to mind, which makes me believe we had ſome pretty Experiments abroad. But as for the Fluids, theſe poor, theſe damn'd Fluids that make us ſick and well, I have ſeen Mr. <hi>Boyl</hi> and ſome others making a great many Experiments upon them; and I have been told that one <hi>Malpighius, Lewenhoeck,</hi> and ſome other Fellows have taken Glaſſes, Spectacles, I don't know how you call them, to look into them; but theſe are Gentlemen
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33737:12"/>
below your notice, and ſo you think <hi>they have been neglected: But the College abounds with Men of ſuch large Capacities;</hi> and Faith ſo it does, and I hope will in ſpite of you, that I hope they'l al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be a doing ſomething worthy of that noble Faculty: But you a fearful defamer, to talk as you have of Phyſicians, ought to be <hi>Scandalum Magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum;</hi> you are convinc d your Book wou'd never be read abroad, and ſo you freely call them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Ignorants, gueſſers, and I don't know what; but your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice too does carry you ſo far, as to defame a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of this College, becauſe he's Dead; another you name, becauſe perhaps his talent is to be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, or to neglect ſuch pretenders as you, and a third forſooth you will not name, tho' you cou'd not conceal him among ſuch as you take to be your Friends; but I'le tell you that when we come to his Story I le name them, and him after you, and let you ſee too that you never expos'd your ſelf more than in relating of that Obſervation; but all this in good time: and if thus you deal under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand with our living Members, and openly with him that is Dead, God have mercy upon the ſhorteſt livers, they'l be ſure to have your Tongue for a Purgatory in a Proteſtant Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>Now your whole Introduction being compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the next Paragraph, I will look into that, and leave the honeſt Gentleman that intruſts you with his Letters, to the mercy of the World.</p>
            <p>
               <q>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I have before ſaid, ſo I ſhall now repent it again, that I may not be miſunderſtood by any one; that tho' I commend Acids in the Cure of Diſeaſes, yet I do not pretend that any one Acid will anſwer all Intentions, there being a mighty difference in the Operation and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Acids. That Acid that will Cure an Acute Diſtemper (generally ſpeaking) will not cure a Chronical one. I have generally obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that volatile Acids are moſt effectual in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33737:13"/>
Acute Diſtempers, and fix'd ones in thoſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers we call Chronick ones. But in theſe every Man's practice muſt be regulated and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd by Obſervation: For as Phyſick had its Riſe and Original from Obſervation, ſo I am ſure that by obſervation only it is capable of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought to perfection.</q>
            </p>
            <p>What greater confuſion can any Man diſcover, than there is here in theſe few lines; if his only, and certain principles can give him no greater Lights and Notions in his Study and beloved O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, the Lord have mercy upon thoſe Patients from whom he's to gather the Hiſtory of Diſeaſes! and if we ſtammer ſo in explaining our ſelves, our common diſcourſe muſt needs be ſelf-evident. Pray, why don't you at leaſt tell us a Story of thoſe vaſt differences that are in the Operations of Acids, if you cannot tell me whence that dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference comes? I may very eaſily miſtake one Acid for another, and then play the Devil with my Patient; 'tis true he was convinc'd by his Blood that 'twas Alkalin, and therefore 'twas to be cur'd by an Acid, and then if it does not take, but does him harm he himſelf was judge, but the Diſeaſe did maſter us: Pray, good Mr. Member, What is it that this Acid does with the Fluids? Does it make the Blood run quicker or flower? but I beg your pardon again, for you ſay you know nothing of that. What then do you ſay, <hi>That the Acid that will cure an Acute diſtemper</hi> (generally ſpeaking) <hi>will not cure a Chronical one;</hi> ſo far all's well; for generally, only 'twill not do it; then I may give either without any conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able miſtake; but then <hi>generally</hi> again, you ſay <hi>you have obſerv'd that Violatil Acids are moſt effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al in Acute Diſtempers,</hi> and <hi>fix'd ones in thoſe we call Chronick ones;</hi> now, to ſpeak freely, I do not believe you know the difference betwixt Acute and Chronical diſtempers, as you ſay you call them; for in the Acute Diſeaſes, ſuch Dr. <hi>Willis</hi> and my
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33737:13"/>
other Maſters call Fevers, the Blood ſeems to be all volataliz'd, it flies about like lightning, and therefore every thing that s Volatile, flying <hi>(damn thoſe Latin words)</hi> I think muſt make it fly faſter; and in Chronical Diſtempers, as a Dropſie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> How the Devil wou'd a Sick Man of common Senſe, nay one that's in <hi>Bedlam,</hi> look upon me; if I bid him drink large draughts of fixt Acids. <hi>Vinegar, viz.</hi> as you tell me, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> every hour of the Day. Cure, that won't take, that's too bare faced, and I find you ſmell it, when you leave that to be regulated by ever Man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s Apprentice. Is this the Man that wou d have a Thouſand Pound a Year towards a Labarotary? This is a way to kill more than a Thouſand Pound's worth of Powder and Ball, and he ſays that's ſpent every Year to kill the Enemies abroad, and he wou'd have as much to kill the Friends at home: If it had been the <hi>Jacobites</hi> it had been tolerable, but Friend and Foe, and to give a Fee too to be kill'd, is the Devil and all. But pray, what Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are you like to make? you have only two things to deal with, and theſe are both of a ſort; yet you cannot tell us how to manage them; but there s more in this matter: Diſeaſes don't al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways appear with the ſame face, no not in the ſame perſon at different times; Oh then what can I do? nay any thing, and take a Fee. Now in ſhort, Mr. Member, I le tell you that Phyſick was neither begun, nor can be promoted by ſuch Obſervations. And thus having made a hopeful Introduction; we muſt expect a learned and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful practice, which I now will follow him into, and leave him ſinging his <hi>Io triumph</hi>'s over the learning of the Introduction, by which he has baffled all Foreign Phyſicians, ſome <hi>Dead ones, and all living ones without names.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:33737:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Of the GO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>He begins firſt with the Names the <hi>Gout</hi> has ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd among Phyſicians, when they would tell any one of its having ſeiz'd upon any one part of the Body; tho' this ſorting by-name he ſeems to arrogate to himſelf; but pray Sir do you know that the moſt of the Names you have told us are all Greek, Heathen Greek; and how came they by thoſe names without ranging this Diſeaſe into the ſame order you pretend to: They gave name to the <hi>Sciatica</hi> too; but you have forgot it. But not to inſiſt too long upon Names, where the thing is ſo plain, eſpecially ſince you have afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me more matter to reflect upon, than really I can be at the trouble to conſider; that I will tell you, that 'tis no other than to read your Book, and to write an anſwer; for I have no other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me but your own. And now to begin, you tell us, p. 16. § 3. of the different opinions Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors have vented about the ſeat and original of this Diſeaſe; but I will delay ſpeaking any thing to that ſubject now, becauſe its proper place is a little after this: but ſince you now begin your deſcription, I will tell you that I will have no conſideration about that, ſince your owing it to Dr. <hi>Sydenham</hi> (which is more than you confeſs) has miraculouſly obtain'd him from you the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of <hi>a fair and honeſt man;</hi> and I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent my ſelf to attack you, where you firſt begin to ſhew your Learning, in p. 16. § ult. <q>I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not agree, ſay you, with thoſe Gentlemen, who will have all pain to proceed from a ſolution of Continuity, which in plain <hi>Engliſh</hi> is either a Wound or Ulcer: Now for my part, I can't ſee why we ſhould not be made ſenſible of any thing that injures us, which whatſoever cauſeth pain doth, without deſtroying the Integrity of the parts; and it's plain, whatever cauſeth a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33737:14"/>
ſolution of unity, muſt deſtroy the Integrity of them. Further, <hi>Malbranche</hi> tells us, that our Sences were given us to guard ourſelves from injuries, and that they never fail to anſwer the end for which they were given us: They are never guilty of Deceiving us-; as, for inſtance, our Taſte, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and all theſe proceed from a placid vellication of the Membranes. <hi>Pain</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from a Contraction of the Fibres, and Pleaſure from a pacid relaxation of them) which being granted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> My Maſters the Phyſicians, I aſſure you, do not care whether you agree with them, or not; but why the pox won't you agree with your ſelf? for you ſay that a ſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Continuity, in plain <hi>Engliſh,</hi> is a Wound or an Ulcer, then in the very next paragraph, that <q>a Blow with a blunt thing upon any part, which only bruiſeth it, will occaſion greater pain than if the ſame part were cut with a ſharp in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, although the one only compreſſeth the parts, and the other divides them aſunder, and ſo makes a perfect ſolution of Unity.</q> Now, good Mr. Member, did ever any one but your ſelf call a <hi>Contuſion</hi> by the name of <hi>Wound,</hi> or <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcer?</hi> Nay, I'm convinc'd you will not ſay ſo neither, and I'll undertake to prove to you that pain is a ſolution of Unity, and then you ll ſee that not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Contuſions, but even Wounds and Ulcers, that make more ſenſible ſolutions of Unity, may make pain: yet, ſtill there comes another inconvenience upon the heels of this; for we ſee that the pain of a Contuſion is greater, by your own confeſſion, than the pain by a ſharp inſtrument; yet this pain in a Contuſion is not ſo great, at leaſt not greater than the pain of the Gout, and this you tell us only comes from the ſharp pointed particles that may affect the membranes of the Toe; and do you think then, that thoſe particles have more points, and are ſharper than the Knives and Saw that Surgeons uſe in amputations? but this <hi>en paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpant.</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:33737:15"/>
Now, for the other part, <hi>that we ought to be made ſenſible of any thing that injures us, which what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever cauſeth pain doth, without deſtroying the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity of the parts:</hi> What he means by this I cannot underſtand, neither is it true <hi>Engliſh;</hi> and I don't know any body but will acknowledge that pain makes him ſenſible with a vengeance; but why ſhould we be made ſenſible without deſtroying the integrity of the parts? For a Wound, and an Ulcer, by his own confeſſion, cauſes pain; and yet he ſays too, that in Wounds and Ulcers there is a <hi>ſolution</hi> of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> or the Integrity of the parts broke off. But what a Devil brought Father <hi>Malebranche</hi> hither? was it to let us know he has ſeen his Book <hi>de la recherche de la verit?</hi> More of his works he pretends not to have ſeen, and even that I'm convinc'd he never read in the Original, or <hi>Engliſh</hi> tranſlation, for this proves nothing to his purpoſe: But I'll tell you, good Mr. Member, that the great deſign of that part of the Book you quote, is to prove to us the real deſign and uſe of our ſenſes; ho tells you that they are made ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to our deſign of living, and that in a due diſtance, in a proper Medium, and when there's a <hi>Mens ſana in Corpora ſano</hi> we are never deceiv'd by them in what they repreſent to us; he tells you, that beyond a due diſtance a Houſe that is ſquare will appear round: The reaſon he gives you, but you don't underſtand it; yet he main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, that tho the Houſe is really ſquare, and we apprehend it to be Round, our ſences are not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, becauſe the object is not round at a proper diſtance; but why it appears round rather than of any other Figure he makes very plain: after the ſame manner he tells you, that if you put your black Stick with the white Head (for ſo much only you have of a Fop Doctor) into clear Water, your Stick will appear bent; yet when you pull it out, you find it as ſtraight as it was; and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this Paradox, your Eyes perfectly well,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33737:15"/>
if you but ſaw as <hi>Pere Malebranch</hi> did, your reaſon, wou'd tell you all the time, It is in the water that 'tis very ſtrait. But how comes all this authority in, to condemn poor ſolution of Unity? Is it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he tells you, in the one, that that proceeds from a placid vellication of the Membranes: I don't know he has any neeeſſity to ſay that, but becauſe you quote it from him, and I have not the Book by me, I'll believe you. But what does this vellication make for your purpoſe? <hi>Vellication</hi> to you is <hi>pain,</hi> and nothing that's <hi>placid;</hi> only peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple cannot be kept from ſhowing their reading up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occaſions. And becauſe all this will not do, you wou d palm upon us a deſcription of <hi>pain</hi> and <hi>pleaſure;</hi> that ought to be your own, tho it is not truly ſo; and then wou d make a very ridiculous concluſion, and that without your learned <hi>ergo.</hi> The Concluſion I have no time to conſider, but to the deſcription we ll allow a line or two: and I'll ſuppoſe with you, in another part of this Book, that all ſence proceeds from vibrillation, motion, I don't remember how you expreſs it, of the Nerves, and that <hi>pleaſure</hi> is a more placid relaxati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them, as here: Now, does not the word Relaxation, at firſt view, ſignifie a ſolution of unity: Yet, not to put this hardſhip upon you, let us ſuppoſe, I ſay, that ſence, and every feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in general, is a accompany'd with a vibrilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or trembling of the Nerve, with <hi>viz.</hi> an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternat contraction and diſtraction of the ſame: but theſe motions cannot be perform'd, if there be not a mutual departure or <hi>excurſus</hi> of theſe parts, of which the Nerve is made, in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tact; neither this <hi>excurſus,</hi> but by a ſucceſſive change of their Contact, or in plain <hi>Engliſh,</hi> but by a <hi>ſolution</hi> of Unity; and therefore 'tis evident too, that in all ſenſation there is a ſort of ſolution of Unity, and ſo even pleaſure itſelf is never with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a ſolution of Unity. But becauſe pain is a trembling of greater power, hence it is that that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:33737:16"/>
ſolution which is by pain, is greater and more vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent than in any other feeling; and ſince this gives the doleful feeling alone, this alone may be ſaid to be a <hi>Solution of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> inſomuch that a ſolution of Unity ſignifies or infers a troubleſome ſenſation and feeling. Pray what<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> reaſon can you perſwade us by, that pain proceeds from a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction</hi> of the <hi>Fibres,</hi> and <hi>pleaſure</hi> from a <hi>pacid Relaxation</hi> of them? Theſe are indeed moſt peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able words; but what authority have you for this poſitive aſſertion, as you are pleaſed to ſpeak in the following Paragraph. I may agree with you that pain may be by a ſtagnation of the Juices, but not by a compreſſion, but a diſtention of the veſſels that this feeling is made, and of this you are ſo very fond, that you aſſert that there can be no pain but by a ſtagnation; entirely forgetting the pain we talk'd of but now when a cutting. But pray when the Blood is upon occaſions penn'd up in any Veſſel, ſo that the obſtructing power is greater than that of the approaching Blood, can any Man think that this greater quantity will ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther contract the Veſſel or dilate it? I'm ſure if it does the laſt, the pain that attends it muſt be a ſolution of Unity, as I explain'd before. The ſame's to be ſaid of the Blood in a neighbouring Veſſel, that does not ſtop any other way, than by the diſtended ſide of the obſtructed veſſel com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing its leſs reſiſting ſide. But pray Mr. Member give us an account of the wonderful flight in the next Paragraph, that poſitive Aſſertion (as you are indeed full of ſuch) by which you wou'd ſo evidently put upon us, a concluſion <hi>ab abſurdo</hi> which is natural from your Doctrine, but not at all from ours; in a palſie there is a waſting and a decay of the Member, and a Man might ſay that it is contracted; and if ſo, ſuppoſing your Aſſertion, there ought to be a great deal of pain, which indeed is contrary to Experience: on the other hand ſuch waſtings and decays of Members
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33737:16"/>
are far from the conditions we prov'd to be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in feeling, and ſtill further from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of pain; and therefore (or <hi>ergo)</hi> this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience you have brought in, deſtroys your Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potheſis, but mightily eſtabliſhes what I prov'd to you before. All I will add to this, is, that if you ever have the impudence to ſhow your talent to the World once more, you will not aſſert any thing poſitively, and without a foundation too; but eſpecially when you are to run down Men and Opinions both. But to proceed, I paſs over the weak Account you give of the Diſpoſition ſome People at different times have to this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe more than at another time; and we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your Definition, which I'll aſſure you is very far from an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity</hi> Definition, and 'twill pleaſe you mightily, becauſe you hate all the Art of that place, You tell us, that it is <q>Pain of the <hi>Joints,</hi> and parts adjacent, occaſion'd from an extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſated Alkaline Humour, irritates the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>branes of the Joints, and parts adjacent Hitherto,</q> we ſuppoſe with you, that all pain is the Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of Alkaline parts upon thoſe Membranes where the Pain is; but the difference being the Extravaſation upon the Membranes of the Joints that conſtitute the eſſence of the <hi>Gout:</hi> Then all Pains in Joints are <hi>Gouts;</hi> but <hi>Nocturnal</hi> Pains that affect the <hi>Vertebrae,</hi> are Pains in Joints; <hi>Ergo</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturnal Pains are either the <hi>Gout,</hi> which I do not believe you'l aſſert, or elſe your <hi>Definitio non com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petit Definito;</hi> and that's contrary to the Laws of a good Definition: But again, why alkaline parts? they are the moſt innocent, ſmootheſt things in the World; they have no edges, becauſe you tell us their <hi>Antagoniſt</hi>'s have; then ſuppoſing that theſe were Extravaſated, and this condition cou'd effect the Membranes, we cannot ſee how 'twould irritate them; but you prove afterwards, that theſe are the offending Particles, and there's no ſtanding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your Arguments; <hi>Ergo,</hi> they may be true,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33737:17"/>
tho<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not hitherto. Well let's get another ſtep forward, and ſee what neceſſity there is for their being Extravaſated; truly I ſee none for it, but a great deal to the contrary: But again, we'll ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them Extravaſated, and as ſharp as you ſay they are, nay even carrying <hi>Chevaux de Friſe</hi> with them, yet I don't believe they could provoke Pain, and my reaſon is, that I have been told by ſome of my Maſters that <hi>Aq. Fortis</hi> applied to a <hi>Membrane</hi> or a <hi>naked Nerve,</hi> not otherways hurt, did excite no Contractions as Convulſions, or the like, and if that be true, as I believe it is, then farewell ſomething elſe, and your excellent Definition; which indeed, I believe, you think gone for nothing, but that 'twas never at the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> and you think to put it upon the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity</hi> Doctors.</p>
               <p>Having thus told us the very Nature of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, by this learned Definition, we muſt needs advance and determin the Cure and Original too: You take your ordinary way in Sacrificing <hi>three</hi> or <hi>four</hi> Old Fellows at leaſt, for every thing you are to Eſtabliſh; and becauſe ſome charge the <hi>Head,</hi> others the <hi>Liver,</hi> and your Dear Friend, <hi>Helmont,</hi> the <hi>Stomach,</hi> for troubling us with this Diſeaſe; 'tis below you to charge either: But why did not you tell us who they were that accuſed the Liver and Head, as well as him who accuſed the Stomach? Was it that you do not know? or is it that you'l let the World ſee that your <hi>Devoirs</hi> are only paid to Truth; and in that reſpect down muſt go Friend and Foe, all alike, very Ingenious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. But how do you Refute thoſe old Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; your firſt Argument is <q>from the general Diſorders that precede a Fit.</q> Is this an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to make us fall upon our Friends? Don't you know that a Fit of the Stone makes us vomit, makes our Heads ach, our Limbs as if they were paralitical, makes us Feaveriſh, dry, and makes us ſweat; this is a pretty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> general piece of Diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, and pray, you, did any one carry the Stone
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:33737:17"/>
further than the Kidneys, Ureters, or Bladder Again, as you ſay afterwards, an unclean Stomach makes Impure Chyle, ill Chyle baſe Juices, baſe Juices, the <hi>Gout; ergo,</hi> an unclean Stomach makes the <hi>Gout.</hi> Moreover, do you know that for a long time the Blood, the very Blood, the Store-Houſe of the other Juices was believ'd to be made in the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver;</hi> and if this be true, as I doubt you can't prove the contrary, we ought to go to the firſt thing, ſince we are digging for the Fountain. But ſtill <hi>Malbranch,</hi> another Friend of yours, tells us, that all Pain is in the Brain, and not at all in any part; becauſe, after a Man has loſt his Leg, he frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puts down his Hand to ſcratch the Toe of that Leg that he had lopp'd off ſome time before, and if ſo, we ought to place our Diſeaſe in the Head. 'Tis evident that all theſe <hi>three</hi> cannot be the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal of this Diſeaſe, and I don't tell you how far any of them are ſo: All that I pretend to ſay, is, that any of thoſe old Gentlemen may enjoy their Opinion, notwithſtanding this your firſt Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and now we will ſee if the Second is any better, and that is <q>From the condition of the <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Juices</hi> during the time of the Fit: Under which Head, I ſhall make it appear that the <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Juices</hi> during the time of the <hi>Fit,</hi> abound not with <hi>Acid</hi> Particles, but on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, with <hi>Alkalious</hi> ones.</q> Ha! this a dangerous point to meddle with, here comes in again the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Experiments, demonſtaative <hi>Ergo's,</hi> nay, as he tells us afterwards, as Demonſtrative as any of <hi>Euclid</hi>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s Propoſitions. Is not this a rare Fellow? A rare Promoter and Diſcoverer of Truth, here's a new one indeed, the poor People before him never thought any piece of Learning ſo demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, as any of <hi>Euclid</hi>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s Propoſitions; take any of his, and becauſe, You may have lookt over, or over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lookt the firſt Book, take the <hi>5th.</hi> or <hi>Pythagoras</hi>'s <hi>48th.</hi> and let us ſee the ſame certainty in your Argument, as there is in any one of theſe, you
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:33737:18"/>
think the eaſieſt and moſt uncertain. I have made ſome conſiderable Doubts about your Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, but I cou'd never about his Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in any of theſe following Propoſitions. This ſecond Branch he defers till afterwards, and proceeds now to illuſtrate further his firſt Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but inſtead of doing that, begins already to be jealous of his <hi>Acids</hi> and <hi>Alkalies,</hi> and leaving the Proof of this general Diſorder, or that ſuch a Diſorder is peculiar to this Diſeaſe, as he ought to prove; he only tells us that theſe diſorders are different, according to the different Conſtitutions, and then going to tell us that Alkalies are always the cauſe of Feavers, but never <hi>Acids,</hi> he falls again into a mad Fit; could he think, that the old Gentlemen were to be juſtled our of their Seats by ſo ſmall a touch; tho' he thought, he had ſet them upon rotten Chairs, altogether fit for that purpoſe; I dont know how much in the right, or in the wrong any body ſuppoſes them to be; but 'm ſure every body will ſay, that you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver attempt to deſtroy their Opinions, otherways than by an old trick of your own, a <hi>poſitive</hi> Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is not only unmannerly enough, and like a young Univerſity Man, but you are even pleas'd to grace ſuch Aſſertions with the Title of <hi>Demonſtration;</hi> and you won't ſtop there neither, but they are as evident as <hi>Euclid's</hi> Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. But again, I'll ſuppoſe that you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Buſineſs of Conſtitutions, and that a Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is always one of thoſe general Diſorders, how the Devil came in Acids and Alkalies, in the proof of general Diſorders proceeding a Fit of the <hi>Gout:</hi> you did always, and evidently prove that the Juices, and Juices alone were the ſource of the Diſeaſe; but if you think, that you had made a cunning Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat into your Circle, 'tis done ſo ill that I will not follow you at this time; your ſafety there, after what has been ſaid in the Introduction, being ſenſible and obvious even to your ſelf; but we ſhall
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33737:18"/>
have an occaſion afterwards to talk upon this matter.: Only I muſt tell you, that I ll always ſuppoſe after this, that 'tis the damn<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d <hi>Alkalies</hi> that makes all the Fermentations, and that the <hi>Acids</hi> check them; and I do aſſure you, that this Foundation will go a great way againſt you. Your Hiſtory, Sir, which you now begin very abruptly, and like an ill Taylor ſowing together two pieces of Cloath, you joyn things very ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily, you follow Dr. <hi>Sidenham</hi> cloſe, but you bring him in by the Head and Shoulders. I told you, before, I had nothing to ſay to that great Man; and therefore I'll begin with another Botch of yours, after you have done with him, where <hi>p. 23. §. ult.</hi> you are ſo afraid of your Alkaline Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, that you carry them always in your Pocket, leſt at any time you might miſplace them, and juſt after you have ended Dr. <hi>Sydenham</hi>'s Hiſtory, you begin ſo; <q>The Blood abounding with too great a quantity of <hi>Alkalious Particles,</hi> is the general Cauſe of this Diſtemper, in order to which, there are ſeveral other things which concur: </q>As firſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Is not this handſomly added to the Tail of your Hiſtory; but theſe things you diſpiſe, that is an Univerſity Gloſs; yet even, that is neceſſary for thoſe that would play the plagiary, and not be ſo eaſily diſcovered, for whether I ever had read Dr. <hi>Sydenham</hi> or not, I muſt ſee this is a <hi>Wen</hi> in your Book; but you being too wiſe to be inſtructed, and I ſeeking information every where, and thinking to find it with you, who are a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moter of new Truths, one who would have the World to take nothing upon your Authority, but Demonſtrates every thing; I intend to try, if I can diſcover any greater certainty in your concurring Cauſes, than I have found in the reſt. But to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, I think a way of Aphoriſm in tbis matter wou'd have becom d your aſſerting deſign, better than to tell us, you are to ſay nothing without a Reaſon, and at the ſame time not one reaſon you
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33737:19"/>
give for any thing. <q>Firſt, ſay you, too moiſt a State of Air, which hinders free Tranſpiration, by which means the Excrementitious Alkaline parts, which ſhould be thrown out by the Cuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous Pores, are retained, and the quantity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> Now ſince you are talking of Magick, pray tell me, dear, good, Learned Member of the Royal College, who it is that manages matters ſo exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly within, that only theſe Excrementitious Alka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies are thrown out; and why not rather the Acids, who you ſay are ſharp, half Pikes, Spades and Mattocks; ſurely I wou<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d think that a Body of armed Men are better for breaking into an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>campment (that I may ſpeak ſo, ſince you have brought thoſe fine words out of <hi>Flanders)</hi> than a parcel of Boors, ſluggards, and heavy fellows that have no Arms at all; beſides, a Maſter of mine in a Latin Book of his, treating about this buſineſs of perſpiration (as he calls it) thinks it a ſtrange Paradox, to aſſert that the heavieſt Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are eaſieſt mov'd; or to your underſtanding, that the moſt <hi>Volatile</hi> things are the leaſt apt to riſe, or be ſublim'd; and the moſt earthly things the eaſieſt: but to ſay no more of this Paradoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal nonſenſe, I muſt tell you that perhaps the Tranſpiration is not ſo free in moiſt, as it is in clear weather; yet you give us no reaſon for it; on the contrary, becauſe you are a wonderful fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low at experiments, I'le tell you, that the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration ought to be more free in moiſt weather, than in clear; if you'll only grant me that if there are two fellows meeting at a Door, and by plain force the one keeps the other not only out, but makes his way forward too, this fellow is to be thought the ſtrongeſt; now, only grant me this, and then I'le add, that becauſe you ſay, in clear weather, our ſteems can get clear thorow the pores, theſe doors of our Skin, that they'll much more eaſily get through in moiſt weather; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by a certain experiment, which at this time
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:33737:19"/>
ſhall be nameleſs, the Air is a great deal heavier, juſtles more, and preſles againſt our departing ſteems with greater force than when it is moiſt. You ſee now, How well you demonſtrate. I have no time to inſiſt upon your Prophane, and ill made parallel that follows; neither much to the ſecond Article, ſince you neither prove why variety of Meats, or a great deal of any one ſort is hurtful; and again you make a moſt experimental paralel betwixt the Stomach and the Root of a Tree; It may be good Enthuſiaſm, but 'tis far from a Man of ſo nice experiments as you pretend to be. The third concurring cauſe is aſtoniſhing, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for the wonderful way you have in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging it; we muſt drink Wine, and not drink it. We muſt not drink it, becauſe the Spirits of the Wine meeting with the Volatile Alkalious ſalt of the Blood, by a mutual combination of them, they are turn'd into <hi>Helmont</hi>'s <hi>Offa abba,</hi> which can by no means Circulate with the Blood; I can ſmell the Experiment this your aſſertion depends upon, but I'le tell you that it wants a little Labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratory-work before that is done; for eſpecially, you ought not to have talk'd of Wine, but Spirit of Wine; which has other affections, properties and powers than Wine it ſelf; then you ought to prove that this Alkalious ſalt is ſo plentiful, and in ſo great an abundance in the Blood; and I peremptorily challenge you to anſwer me upon all the integrity you have left you, whether or no you can by the help of your Fire ſhow me a real volatile Salt, or Spirit from any kind of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (for out of healthy Blood is allow'd to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible) Blood new let out of the Veſſel, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſort of Digeſtion; and if this be but true, your reaſon will not debar us from drinking of Wine; but again, you ſay that Wine drank in any great quantity makes them loſe their Tenſity; and if ſo, they are more Relax, and when they are more Relax, they are in the circumſtances
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33737:20"/>
you place them, when they are to be the Inſtruments of our pleaſure; but at this time they are the Cauſes of the <hi>Gout,</hi> and before of pleaſure, and therefore Wine muſt not be drank, becauſe it makes the <hi>Gout</hi> a pleaſure, or a pleaſant, delightful, deſirable <hi>Gout:</hi> O brave Member, Is this the reſult of your reaſoning? Yet, 'tis not fair dealing to remember what was ſaid a Page or two before, and therefore, I'll leave this part, and ſee why we muſt drink it; <q>a ſmall quantity of Wine, <hi>ſaith the Member,</hi> drank at convenient ſeaſons doth raiſe the Spirits, and invigorate the Nerves.</q> Now ſuppoſing all this to be true, how are the Vinous Spirits hindred, and kept from combining and taking counſel with the Alkalious Particles, ſo as not to make that damnable, immoveable <hi>Offa Alba;</hi> they will not do it now, becauſe you will not have it ſo; but you are ſo fond of this Tenſity and Relaxation, that nothing can be more; muſt I tell you, that I'm told, (becauſe I'm no Book Learned Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man) that this was an overſight of <hi>Des Cartes</hi>'s, and perhaps you have ſeen it in <hi>Malbranch,</hi> they tell you indeed, that a Rope ſtretch'd and bent a hundred Yards in length, cannot be ſtruck at one end, but 'twill move at the other; yet can any Man be ſo blind, but he muſt ſee that this is not the condition of the Nerves, for they are ſeen no where to be ſo, but juſt where they come out of the Brain; but if you will try an Experiment that will come nearer the Condition of the Nerves, take a Rope of what length you pleaſe, nail it hard to a Beam, then ſtretch it out in a Spiral or any other Figure, half a Foot more, then nail it again at the end of that half Foot, and ſo all a long 'till you have nail<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d Forty Yards if you will; that this may be liker the Nerves implanted ſo firmly in Muſcles, that they make but one Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; only I muſt deſire you to leave a Yard, or a Yard and a half after the laſt nailing, fitted with
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:33737:20"/>
a Nooze for your Neck, then go in and ſwing ſo long that one that you may think a fair judge, may cut you down when he obſerves the end that was firſt nailed begin to move, vibrillat, and ſhake, then indeed, when you give me an account of this Experiment, you ſhall be allow'd to talk of <hi>Tenſity</hi> and <hi>Relaxation</hi> as you think fit.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Fourthly, <hi>ſay you,</hi> the immoderate uſe of vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real exerciſes, for that it ſpendeth the Spirits, and decayeth Natural heat, and ſo procureth a weakneſs to all the parts of the Body, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> Good Member, if I had but time and patience enough, I cou'd ſhow you that there is not one ſentence in this whole Paragraph that's either conſiſtent and agreeable not only with common Senſe, but ev'n your ſelf too; yet not to paſs it over without ſome remarks, I muſt ask you why the matter may not be ſo contriv'd, that the uſeleſs Alkalin parts may be thrown off in this evacuation, as well as by perſpiration before, and afterwards by the <hi>Counſes</hi> in Women? again, Pray are venereal exerciſes, <hi>Acid</hi> or <hi>Alkalin?</hi> Moreover, a little di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion with a Girl muſt needs be a very good Cure for the <hi>Gout,</hi> according to you; becauſe the Fever you told us before, which is made by that deviliſh fermenting Alkali, intimates to us the neceſſity of ſomething that may hinder this fermentation, and allay this Heat; and now you tell us, upon this occaſion, that it decayeth Natural heat, and a little of it we want to have decay'd, that we may cure the Gout and Fever; <hi>ergo</hi> a touch or two muſt be very uſeful for Gouty People, which is <hi>contra hypotheſin &amp; experientiam,</hi> tho' no unnatural conſequence of your reaſoning. I promis'd indeed not to ſay one word more to this Paragraph, but you think when a Man has read the inſtitutions, that he's ſtraight fitted not only to be a Phyſician, but a great Author; and therefore whether it be to the purpoſe or no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, or rather playing at croſs purpoſes, you will
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33737:21"/>
ſhow your talent there, in a long ſtory of volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary and involuntary motion; where you are pleas'd to be the firſt that ever reckoned Reſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion among the involuntary motions; 'tis a diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of your own I confeſs, and no body that I know will diſpute it with you, tho' I muſt tell you that I can keep my breath a minute or two, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding my performing that action three or four times in that ſpace of time, when I do not contrive and order it ſo. Your way of deſcribing Involuntary motions is peculiar to your ſelf too, for I have <hi>walk'd</hi> in my ſleep, I have <hi>talk'd</hi> and yet walking and talking were never call'd invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary motions by any one but you ſelf; <hi>ergo,</hi> I think that you your ſelf ought to read the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Medicin before you begin not only to teach, but even to run down others. As to the fifth concurring Cauſe, I'le only deſire you to tell me whether Sleep or over-much ſleep in the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon is Acid or Alkali; Alkali it muſt be, but how do you prove it? for further upon this Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph I will not attempt, becauſe I really tell you That in that whole letter of Dr. <hi>Cole</hi>'s, about an apoplexy, where you read this, I believe 'tis the moſt unlucky, ill ſpoke thing in the whole Book, and ſo the Dr. your good Friend, is not only very much oblig'd to you for bringing him upon the ſtage, but for joining him too with your <hi>Novum Lumen Chyrurgicum;</hi> which I muſt tell you is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter nonſenſe ev'n than your Treatiſe of the Gout, if that is poſſible. But to paſs over at this time, your 6thly, 7thly, 8htly, 9thly and 10thly; both becauſe I want time, and theſe are the moſt inconſiderable, and laſtly, That you cannot write another Book without them, and ſo we'll leave them yours untoucht, only I muſt deſire you'll pleaſe to inform me how <q>overmuch Watching and Faſting, and Study, and Sorrow, and Care, and much Labour, over-much Reſt, ſudden Reſt, expoſing the Body to the Air in cold or
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33737:21"/>
moiſt Seaſons, after any violent Exerciſe, the total leaving off of any accuſtomed Exerciſe, the keeping the Feet either too Hot or too Cold, are Alkalies;</q> For theſe they are; but how, is my deſire to know. And now to your <hi>Eleventhly,</hi> becauſe tho' I am old, yet I like a little baudy as well as you, and this we cannot paſs over with the reſt, without an unpardonable neglect, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of your exact obſervations on this point. Eleventhly, ſay you, <hi>from the ſtopping of any uſual evacuation, as the Monthly Courſes in Women, and a Flux of the</hi> Hemorrhoids <hi>in Men, which I have frequently known to keep their certain periods to a Day, by means of which obſervation the Excremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titious Matter wanting its uſual vent is tranſmitted to ſome other part of the Body. And according to the nature of the Part upon which it is thrown, it exerciſeth its Tyranny accordingly.</hi> This is a trick indeed, good Member, you tell the Women that you know that they have Monthly Courſes, and that you have kept a correſpondence with ſo many of them, that after all your long conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, you have met with ſome of them that have gone to Day; now more than this, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not learn from this branch; you that are a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former, are you not yet free of the vulgar Error of the Blood of the Monthly Courſes being rank Poiſon, do you think ſtill that one drop of this Blood can deſtroy whole Corn-fields, the periodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation or the neceſſity of having ſuch Courſes has been a very hard task to Phyſicians to account for, but I remember that one of my Maſters in my Dedication proves very evidently, that the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruous Blood muſt be the ſame, in every reſpect, with the reſt of the Blood running in the Arteries; excepting any impurity it may contract, by the way, in the <hi>Vagina <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>teri,</hi> or further in its way of coming out; ſo however certain it may be that Women are not ſo apt to have the Gout, and ev'n other Diſeaſes, ſo long as they keep time in that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:33737:22"/>
Monthly Evacuation, yet this is not becauſe there is an Evacuation of <hi>Morbifick</hi> Matter, or of Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that may occaſion Diſeaſes, and really no more than the Key that ſticks in your Laboratory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>door, when you make an Experiment, can be ſaid to be the contriver and manager of it. But pray, ſuppoſing all this were true, what's the neceſſity of this matter's affecting the Joints more than any other place? you ſay nothing of this all along.</p>
               <p>Having thus diſtinctly ſhown that you have not at all <q>diſtinctly given an account of all thoſe things which either cauſe the Gout at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining, or accelerate a fit on thoſe People who have already received the Morbifick impreſſion, and alſo of the general diſorders that precede a Fit;</q> I will now proceed with you to your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and beloved Head; which is, <q>That the Blood and Juices during the time of the Fit abound not with <hi>Acid Particles,</hi> but on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> with <hi>Alkalious</hi> ones.</q> And becauſe I hate Totologies as well as you do, I wiſh you wou'd make us happy with this Hiſtory of Human Blood of yours, that we are thus plagu'd with; but let me adviſe you, for a better guide, to lay before you an <hi>apparatus</hi> to ſuch a Hiſtory, I am told that Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi> has left you; but tis very probable that a Book-learn'd Gentleman of his ſmall Capacity is unworthy of your notice. Yet to ſay no more of this, you delay your giving us an account of the ſtate and condition of Human Blood in the time of a Fit, till you bleſs the World with this your Experimental Hiſtory, for which your other Books are but ſo many obſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porous Trumpets for a Poppit-ſhow; ſo we muſt wait with patience, and, in the mean time, hear what elſe you are pleas'd to dictate upon this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, which is, that <q>beſides the neceſſary Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions to be made from reiterated Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Diſtilling, or Analizing by Fire the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:33737:22"/>
Blood of thoſe People who labour under the Fit of the Gout, the generating of the Chalky Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance contained in the Node during that time, and thoſe Nodes nor that chalky Subſtance are at any other time produced, but during the very time of the Fit; from this very production alone, it plainly appears that the Blood, and other Juices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> Here I ſet your <hi>Achillean</hi> Argument in its beſt and moſt favourable Light, and after I tell you that, I paſs your rediculous ſtuff about this matter, being bred all in one Fit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I muſt enquire of you, what this proves in the general about the Alkality of the Blood in the time of any Sickneſs; and then I'll tell you that 'tis not againſt the Doctrine eſtabliſh'd before, upon ſuppoſing the Truth of Acid and Alkali, being the real Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Bodies; tho' at the ſame time, Dr. <hi>Blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard</hi> tells you, that you <hi>Chymiſts,</hi> (as you pleaſe to title your ſelf) ſay that all Fermentation ariſes from the Combination of Acid and Alkali, tho' you ſay moſt aſtoniſhingly from the Alkali only; but you are both agreed that Acids are more the cauſes of Quiet or Reſt; now Quiet is a neceſſary requiſite for Petrification, and conſequently that the Acids is more fit to make the parts of this Stony and Chalky Subſtance unite; but a great deal more than that buſtling Alkali that cauſes Fermentation and Diſunion of parts: but again, I muſt tell you, that you will not have it an Alkali neither, for you lay this as a general Truth, that whatever changes a Solution of Syrup of Violets with water, or an Aqueous Body into Green, is an Alkali; and now you tell us, that <q>when this Chalky Subſtance is Calcin'd, it will turn Syrup of Violets Green, and ſometimes (tho' not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways) will do the ſame without Calcination.</q> Here is indeed <hi>Chymical</hi> Senſe, every thing that changes Syrup of Violets diſſolv'd in Water, into a Green Colour, is an Alkaline Subſtance, the <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ky</hi> Stuff taken out of <hi>Gouty</hi> Nodes ſeldom do it,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:33737:23"/>
                  <hi>ergo</hi> 'tis an Alkali, poſitively Alkali; Is not this a hopeful Concluſion? But, Sir, I know you deſpiſe the Maxims of my poor old Maſters, that have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways told us that the cauſe and effect are the ſame, or the cauſe and effect are always together, and never ſeparated; here by a piece of ſublimated Knowledge, you tell us, that 'tis the Eſſence of an Alkali, which makes us call a Body ſo, becauſe it works theſe changes upon your Syrup of Violets, yet here's no ſuch change; but yet it muſt be an Alkali: How are you to be underſtood? 'Tis an Alkali, and 'tis not an Alkali; well, but ſay you, Calcine, it then it will do; but pray, why muſt I Calcine it? that it might be more <hi>Homoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous</hi> as you call it, and liker what it is in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; but how am I ſure that there is ſuch a Fire in our Bodies, and a <hi>Chymiſt</hi> that makes theſe Alka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, or that the Fire has made this Subſtance more natural; ſome change it has undergone, it did not change your Syrup, now it does, but is it become more natural? But theſe are things of common Senſe, and you <hi>Chymiſts</hi> deſpiſe all that; and therefore. I tell you, that I'll leave all the reſt of this damn'd Jargon, and your whole II Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter too, about the Regulation of the <hi>non Naturales,</hi> as you call them, becauſe I would only vindicate my old Maſters, and have a touch at your belov'd Medicine before I've done; yet I muſt tell you that Dr. <hi>Garth</hi> in his Lecture proved it evidently, that no Air was mixt with the Blood in the Lungs, and another ſaid, that it would make it leſs Fluxil if it was ſo; and becauſe People live moſt upon Air by your Experiment which you bring us; I wou'd adviſe you to get into a Glaſs Veſſel with a cover that's peirced, to let in the Air, then Subſtracting two thirds of your ordinary al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance becauſe of the Experiment, and a half of the other third, becauſe you now are quiet, and do not perſpire ſo much as when you go about in your Coach and ſmoke Tobacco in the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:33737:23"/>
Coffee-Houſes, and then we'll know more of the matter. But let's leave this, and look in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your III. Chapter, and there you tell us that, <q>To Demonſtrate the Inſufficiency of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of Cure, both heretofore, and at this time in common practice by the generality of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians; for the well performance of which, I ſhall give you the whole Method taken by a great Phyſician, Sir <hi>John Gordon</hi> ſince dead, with a Noble Lord, the Lord <hi>Carliſle,</hi> he uſed all the Alkalious Medicines, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> He was a Man very fit to teach you Mr. <hi>Member,</hi> both by Inſtructing you in any part of Phyſick, and curbing that inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, impudent forwardneſs of yours, and 'tis well you have nick'd the time ſo well, as to accuſe him after he is Dead, and when he may have no Friend out of his own Country; but I can aſſure you for once, that his Death was very much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gretted by worthy and learned People, that had known his dextrerous Hand in ordering, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſting a Medicine; his Merits I acknowledge are as far above my praiſe, as they are above your ſnarling; and therefore I will only ask, why this great Man was to expiate for former, and preſent Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians? he never told you that 'twas the Gout he was to cure my Lord <hi>Carliſle</hi> of, and how come you to know it? were not there Books of former Phyſicians that told you, I give Alkalies for the Gout, and Phyſicians alive that juſtify this practice; why was not their Blood to be ſprinkled before your Threſhold? dead Authors may have defenders, and live ones will; but here's a Man for the purpoſe, he has few Friends here, and my Books being only deſign'd for the Mob, they are not only not read here, but they're ſure never to go into <hi>Scotland.</hi> Yet, may I preſume to tell you, that the uſage of the <hi>French</hi> in diſturbing the Aſhes of the Dead at <hi>Hailbron</hi> Two Years ago, after they had taken it, was reckon'd a piece of the moſt inhuman and barbarous Cruelty that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33737:24"/>
ever was heard of. They were incens'd Enemies, and might have done it in fury and in a mad fit; but for you to do almoſt the ſame thing, and more, conſidering the circumſtances, is unpardonable: It not only ſhows the meanneſs of your Soul, but the apprehenſions you lye under as to other Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians of your own time. But when did you learn this Story? was it about the time, that you had the impudence to come in upon the practice of one of the greateſt, and juſtly eminent Chyrurgeons of this Town, for my Lady <hi>Carlile,</hi> and was in a very ſhort time after ſent a packing for your ſucceſs? truly this is a very remarkable occaſion! and as I was ſaying to you but now, How did Mr. <hi>Nicholſon</hi> or you either know, ſo certainly as to venture to defame a Man, that Sir <hi>J. G.</hi> was to cure that Noble Lord of the <hi>Gout?</hi> Again, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing it was ſo, you cannot prove by all that is ſaid that this was not a good practice, but ev'n that it was not the beſt: then, <hi>ſay you,</hi> Why was not he curd? Becauſe he was incurable, and I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Sir <hi>J. G.</hi> told him ſo: and when all this is done, is Sir <hi>John</hi> or the whole Art of Phyſick to be ridicul'd, becauſe it cannot immortalize Men? or have you attain'd to that certainty that you can keep a Man from dying of any one Diſeaſe? truly, I have heard one of my great Maſters ſay, that he wou'd value himſelf mightily, if he cou'd but certainly cure Corns: but more than this you can do; tho' if I had time, I cou'd very eaſily demonſtrate (ſince that is the word) that your own practice, for which you have ſhed ſo much Blood, attack'd ſo many reputations, or made ſo many hecatombs, is the moſt ridiculous ſtuff in nature: but I'm ſure thoſe that are as mad as your ſelf to try it, will find the event by a great and running name.</p>
               <p>And now ſince I am brought ſo near an end, and am forc'd to skip a great many nonſenſical Things hat fall a courſe, conſidering the former ruines;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:33737:24"/>
I'le content my ſelf with looking into your ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations about Fevers, that I may ſee how diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet you are to ſome living Phyſicians, and how well you ſhow your own underſtanding, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faming them.</p>
               <p>In the firſt obſervation, you are a great deal kinder than you have hitherto ſhow'd your ſelf; you tell us here of a Lady of great worth (as all your Patients are) that was ill treated, by ſome friend or diſciple of yours, 'twou'd ſeem, becauſe you you have not given us his name; this Lady is juſt a going down into the Chambers of Death, and her Friends expreſſing their loſs by their Tears, when in comes the Great <hi>Colbatch</hi> with a ſaving <hi>Acid,</hi> and gives them better hopes of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting Friend. Well done 'faith, Mr. Member; but who the Devil, do you think, will believe that you cur'd a deplorable Patient of a Hectick Fever, in 12 Days eſpecially? I will not doubt of a Cure of ſomething perform'd in that time, but that you know what a Hectick Fever is, I mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doubt. And that theſe your Medicines may be of uſe to the World, as you ſay you deſign them, you ought to have given us a true Obſervation, or an exact Hiſtory of the circumſtances of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Patient, which you neither do in all theſe Obſervations, nor do I believe you capable to do it. But laſtly, you give us a fine example of what you wou'd do, for curing a Hectick Fever; which is ſo fine, that I think the College ought to Fine you <hi>excre tuo</hi> for a <hi>mala praxis:</hi> but if I were to obſerve all the miſtakes you make in every particular in this and the other Obſervations (as you pleaſe to call them) I ſhou'd put an endleſs task upon my ſelf: You know that is not my main deſign, but the Vindication of my Maſters, and therefore to paſs your ſecond Obſervation with one Queſtion only, we ſhall be brought to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: now the Queſtion is, <hi>Whether or no the giving a Vomit to ſuch a Patient as you deſcribe here, before
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:33737:25"/>
you let him Blood, is not the real cauſe of all the ſwellings of his Face, that brought him into ſo great danger through the whole Cure?</hi> I am apt to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that if that were determin'd too, there wou'd be another Twenty pound. To the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe again, as much as your croſs-purpoſe will allow us; you promis'd us an account of Fevers cur'd by Acids, but inſtead of that you will bring in, over head and ears, a Story to abuſe Dr. <hi>Richard Robinſon;</hi> and that is of an Apoplexy; the fact, I mightily doubt of, as of all yours, you make them ſo monſtrous to ſhow your skill, that they are not to be believed; here's now a living Phyſician, and therefore I will not preſume to vindicate him, becauſe he is more able, in every reſpect, than I am; and will not obſerve your ridiculous cure of a radicated Phtiſis, as you call it, becauſe the deſcription is like all thoſe of your own co ntrivance, very Originals for Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe: who ever deſcrib'd a <hi>Phtiſis Pulmnum</hi> as you do, or cur'd ſo ſoon ſuch an one as you wou'd deſcribe. Now you come into Fevers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and to make the ſtory more formidable, you tell us of a fearful <hi>Peſtilential Fever,</hi> wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully deſcrib'd, but manag'd by an Honeſt and Great Phyſician; very well Member, good words indeed; But did you never tell over the Town who this Great Phyſician was? Yes, you did, 'twas Dr. <hi>G—s</hi> a very learned and great Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, I do aſſure you, and one of the faireſt Practitioners about Town; but how the Patient was manag'd, what his Conſtitution was, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> you ſay nothing of: You tell us he had a bleeding at the Noſe for Thirty hours, and that 'twas ſtopt by your <hi>Vulnerary Powder,</hi> and that he was cur'd by you afterwards. Was not all this very great, to come in upon an Honeſt Phyſician and to Cure his Patient? Your Vulnerary Powder you are ſo fond of, will be conſider'd anon; but 'tis always your good luck to expoſe your ſelf moſt,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:33737:25"/>
where you expect the greateſt Applauſe, 'tis hard to have to do with Great Phyſicians: they have deſigns you can dream nothing of; you tell us, you ſtopt the Bleeding, yet the Fever continued; now the ſame doubts remains with me, that it ſeems did with Dr. <hi>G.</hi> this evacuationſeem'd to be critical, and 'tis an old Maxim founded upon Obſervation, that <hi>Nulla Criſis eſt Parca,</hi> and ſome of my Maſters have told us the reaſon of it; ſo that 'tis more than probable that the Fever would then have been cur'd, if you had not ſtopt the Bleeding too ſoon, and was really cured by the very ſame Evacuation, and perhaps was then cured for all your ſaying ſo; I do not accuſe your honeſty in this point, but your knowledge; for a Man that cannot tell me when any one has a Fever, at leaſt the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Circumſtances can never tell me when he Cures one, and this is much your Caſe: For ſince you do all for the good of Mankind, and all the World knows we want exact Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, and Accounts of Fevers, more than Medicines; give us firſt a good Indication, Inſtruments can never be wanting, Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Bread, and a Bottle of Water, will do very often with a great many: Let me add to all this, that I think a <hi>Mala praxis</hi> is more juſtly your Reward than any thing elſe; you need not be afraid of that Doctor, for you are too much below his wrath.</p>
               <p>We have ſeen enough of your Talent of Writing, your excellent art in deſcribing Diſeaſes, your ſingular, but unlucky way of Defaming Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, and a great deal of a ridiculous Practice, ſuppoſing your deſcriptions were natural, or in plain <hi>Engliſh,</hi> we ſee how honeſt, and how learned a Phyſician you are, and that really you are too much honourd, even with my notice of your Book; and therefore ſince I have begun, I'll endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to do you Juſtice about your <hi>Vulnerary Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:33737:26"/>
too, and that from a Letter to you, from your unknown, yet faithful Servant, and Well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſher, <hi>T. S.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I believe indeed, as you do, that he's a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of Candor and Ingenuity, nay and a Prophet too, for he ſaid, you would Write on till you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd your ſelf, which is moſt true. But the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil's in your Impudence for comparing your Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, as you call it, to <hi>Harvey</hi>s Circulation; you accuſe the Ancients of more Ignorance than <hi>Harvey</hi> thought fit to do, and even his Diſcovery it ſelf muſt be leſſen'd by you; if you had been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his time twou'd certainly have been yours; but I'll ſwear, I doubt you underſtand it ſtill, for as evident as it ſeems to you, <q>I admire, <hi>ſay you,</hi> how People could be ſo ſottiſh, as to ſee <hi>Blood</hi> run from a <hi>Vein</hi> below the <hi>Ligature,</hi> and not from thence infer a Circulation.</q> Is this all the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence you have to diſparage <hi>Harvey</hi>'s Diſcovery by, and to entitle you to the liberty of making Dunces of former Phyſicians? Mr. <hi>Member</hi> if I were to Examin you upon this Point, I'm afraid, you ſhould be Remitted to your Studies. Let us ſuppoſe then with the Ancients, that Blood came from the Head, the Liver, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> into the Arms and Legs, and that this Blood was returned by theſe <hi>Veins,</hi> a <hi>Ligature</hi> in this caſe ſtopping the motion of the Blood in its return, obliges the Blood to run out of a Wound that's made below the <hi>Ligature,</hi> as much on this Suppoſition, as upon <hi>Harvey</hi>'s De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, and therefore we hear them talk of Bleeding the <hi>Cephalick</hi> in the Arm for Head-Aches, the <hi>Hepatick</hi> in Inflamations, and the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> in more Ambiguous caſes. You ſee now, how well you underſtand the Circulation; but you confound every thing you meddle with, if it were even a T—d. But after all your boaſting, we return to your Powder that cures Wounds of the Guts, and Lungs certainly; here's Impudence indeed, but for evincing this
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:33737:26"/>
as ſhortly as I can, I'll hint at two or three things about curing of Wounds, and then De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate what a Medicine muſt be, that cures the Wounds in the Lungs in particular. 'Tis agreeable with common Obſervation that Wounds on Muſcles, or in the more muſculare parts are the eaſieſt cured, ſuppoſing our power of coming at them, (which is a Bull of a ſuppoſition were it not made to a Block-head) and conſequently the leſs Muſcular any part is, the leſs capable it is to be cur'd: Now the Lungs are a Congeries of Bladders and Blood Veſlels, and conſequently very hard to grow together; but beſides this, a Medicine that cures the Lungs muſt not only make it grow to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in Fifteen ſeconds, but even ſo, as to contain air againſt its gravity and elaſtical power in that time, which is an infinite force: Now, ſince this is ſo evidently neceſſary, let us ſee if this Medicin can unite and cure a wound in the beſt Circumſtances, in Fifteen ſeconds; and if it cannot do that, or if it cannot cure a Cut-finger in that time, far leſs will it ever cure a Wound in the Lungs; and that this muſt be the time is evident from the buſineſs of Reſpiration.</p>
               <p>Now, for its effects, I can give you a prety good Hiſtory of it from a Maſter of mine, who talkd with my Lord <hi>Cuts</hi> about it, in <hi>Chaves</hi>'s Chocolat-Houſe in the <hi>Pall-Mall,</hi> when my Lord had a deſign to promote his ſingular diſcovery; and a word out of <hi>Flanders</hi> about a Lieutenant Colonel, becauſe he only talks of Granadiers or a Serjeant, then I've done.</p>
               <p>This Nobleman, who I'm told is a very good Friend and promoter of any thing that may be of publick Service, was conducted by this Learned Member to ſee ſome Experiments
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:33737:27"/>
made upon Dogs; he had then the confidence to deſire ſome of the Gentlemen that attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my Lord thither, to run one of the Dogs thorow the Guts, and the other thorow the Lungs as near as they could; which was done, and he dreſs'd up the Dogs, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd to let his Lordſhip ſee them recover'd in Six or Eight Days: My Lord had not ſeen the Event when he talk'd with one of my Maſters about that Affair; but next <hi>Sunday</hi> my Maſter meeting his Lordſhip at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> he ask'd him about his Dogs, who was anſwerd that <hi>Colebatch</hi> had told him that they had made their eſcape: This was ſuch a piece 'of ſtuff that did not take with his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; but anſwering, there's a Granadier of mine run thorow the Lungs and he has him now under his Cure; I am told that my Maſter askt my Lord, if he was ſure that he was run through the Lungs, for Chyrurgeons have not given us any diſtinguiſhing Symptoms in this caſe; but the Lord <hi>Cuts</hi> ſaid of that he cou'd ſay nothing, but that he ſaid he was run through the Lungs: However, my Maſter meeting his Lordſhip again, askt him about the Granadier, who told him that he was Dead. This I may believe was the true reaſon that he never made any further addreſſes to his Lordſhip, he not being very eaſy to be put upon. Then as to <hi>Flanders</hi> tis very well known that Lieutenant Col. <hi>Hume,</hi> of my Lord <hi>Lorne</hi>'s Regiment, got a wound on the Thigh, with a Muſquet Bullet at <hi>Namur,</hi> and ſending for the Member for his Cure, was diſpatcht, before his Friends heard that he was wounded, his Thigh ſwelling pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digiouſly, which next day gangreen'd, of which he died.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:33737:27"/>
Here, good Mr. Member, you have both Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Experience about your Powder, and they are both in their own Nature ſo convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, that I doubt you cannot bring your ſelf off; a little impudence does very well with a Quack, and if you had ſtaid there, you might have been ſafe for me; but Ignorance being once joined with it, no body can be ſafe; You attack my Dead Maſter with a Name, a Living one without a Name, and the whole College in a very plain way: I have told you this once, <hi>Verbum ſapienti ſat eſt,</hi> but a Fool's never to be mended.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:33737:28"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
